Today, we're going to cover the basics of instruction set architectures, or ISAs.
As you learned in 252 and 354, instructions are the words of the computer, and the ISA
is the vocabulary that the processor understands.
The ISA defines the full extent of what software can tell the processor to do.
Well, almost.
We'll cover those later in the course.
The important part about ISAs is that they abstract away the implementation.
Intel's x86 backwards compatibility means that an ad instruction will produce identical
results across multiple generations of processors.
If you still have a desktop PC, you could replace the processor with the latest generation
and your operating system would still boot and your applications would still execute,
just hopefully a little faster and consuming a little less power than before.
Old binaries probably aren't aware of the new instructions, so you might not realize
the full power of the new silicon.
We're going to focus on MIPS and a MIPS like ISA in this class because it's simple, sensible,
and regular.
There aren't many instruction variants that cause problems with implementations.
Another version of our textbook uses an open source ISA called risk five.
Its use may be rising, but it is important for us to think of ISAs like programming languages.
That is, learning MIPS or risk five doesn't mean you'll never have to learn another ISA.
And like programming languages, the more ISAs you know, the more prepared you'll be when
you architect one yourself.
We will first look at the basics of a MIPS instruction, followed by registers and arithmetic
ops.
Finally, we'll cover memory and control instructions like branches and jumps.
At this point, I recommend pausing the video and looking at the MIPS green card from the
textbook or the PDF from the course website.
It covers the instructions and syntax for the assembler and will be a handy reference
as we go through this lecture and the rest of the semester.
Take a look at this single statement in C. C enables a programmer to succinctly describe
the mathematical result that they want stored in variable f.
But unlike the complex please x, y, z example earlier, MIPS doesn't have an instruction
that exactly performs this operation.
MIPS can at maximum perform one step with two inputs at a time, so this C statement must
be decomposed into three MIPS instructions.
MIPS has an add instruction that sums two operands and writes to a destination.
We must temporarily store the sums of g plus h and i plus j.
MIPS also has a subtraction instruction that will subtract two operands and store the result
in a destination.
The MIPS ISA assembly syntax specifies that a mnemonic comes first and the operands come
after.
Generally, the outcome comes next, the output, and the inputs are on the right.
Your MIPS green card will tell you when a mnemonic has a different paradigm.
In a load store ISA like MIPS, operands are registers, not variables.
MIPS has 32 word size registers that can be used, 0 through 31.
Now MIPS also specifies label aliases for these register numbers that dictate conventions
that programmers must follow.
These labels are also found on the MIPS green card.
In this case, registers T0 and T1 are intended to store temporary variables, and they correspond
to physical registers 8 and 9.
At a high level, our processors 32 registers are used as inputs to the ALU and as outputs
to store.
Some example ALU operations include simple arithmetic like add and subtract, and the
logical operations like and and or or shift left and shift right.
The regular add ADD performs signed arithmetic.
Other flavors will take an immediate or performed unsigned addition.
Note that multiply and divide produces 64 bits of output for more precision, so the results
go into a special double word register.
The MIPS green card will tell you how to load the upper and lower results from the into
your 32-bit register file.
Why do we only have 32 registers?
Well, first off, 32 registers uses less silicon area than 64 or 128.
Second, it takes just 5 bits to specify a unique identifier, and that keeps our instruction
words smaller.
But is 32 registers enough?
Generally no, like with long arrays.
We need to be able to load a register for memory and store a register value back to
memory.
To load a 32-bit word for memory, this load word instruction will cause the address stored
in S1 to be loaded into register T1.
On the flip side, store word will store the value in T1 to the address stored in register
S0.
This is an example of the ISA subtly changing the ordering of source and destination.
Memory typically lives outside the processor chip, though maybe not outside the package
of the processor as 2.5D advanced manufacturing puts multiple chiplets on the same interposer.
Memory is byte-addressed, meaning our variable f is stored in the across addresses 4004,
4005, 4006, and 4007.
Using memory is important for arrays.
Say we need to add h to every index of array a.
Before we get started, I want to highlight the parentheses used in load and store.
S5, by itself, refers to the value stored in register S5.
The parentheses around S5 refer to the value stored in memory at the address contained in
S5.
If this were C, register S5 would contain the pointer, and parentheses S5 parentheses
would contain the value we are loading.
In this example, T0 is our temporary holding spot for the data after a load and before the
store.
Enter S2 contains our constant h, and S5 contains the index multiplied by 4 because we need
a 4-byte word address, not a byte address.
Finally, the address to the zeroth index of a is at 8000.
This could also be called the base address.
Looking at the code, first we load from address 8000 plus the ith word and store it in T0.
Next we add the value of h to T0.
Finally we store T0 back to the same address we loaded it from.
Our update is complete.
MIPS has other load store instructions for bytes and half words should the application
require it.
How do we deal with loops?
In this snippet of C code, the while loop is going to repeat while i does not equal
j.
We don't know how many loops through this code will be required, so let's convert this
to MIPS.
Let's assign i and j to S1 and S2 and assign address labels to the beginning of this while
loop and the location just after the closing scope.
MIPS provide branch instructions that activate when the operands are equal and when the operands
are not equal.
Let's look at this loop again.
We want to enter the loop only if i is not equal to j, so we must branch to the end if
they're equal.
So our first instruction at the beginning of the loop will branch to the end if we want
to exit.
If we don't take the branch, MIPS will execute the next instruction and stay inside the loop.
At the bottom we'll have an unconditional jump back to the top.
What does branch equal really do?
Well, first it reads the register values in S1 and S2 and then compares.
Depending on the comparison result, it will either set PC to the next word instruction
or it'll set PC to target.
The program counter or PC specifies the address of the currently executing instruction.
To do comparisons other than equal equal or not equal, MIPS provides some pseudo instructions.
For example, branch less than is a pseudo instruction.
What it really does is it executes two instructions.
It sets less than and then it branches not equal to zero.
For MIPS branches, branch equal S1, S2 and immediate allows us to specify the offset.
There's also a branch not equal.
There's set less than, set less than or equal and then also greater than and greater than
equal.
Finally, we have unconditional jumps.
We can just straight up jump to a new address.
We can jump to an address stored in a register and we can jump and link, which is used for
function calls.
Jump and link link first sets the return address to PC plus eight and then it sets the PC to
the address specified.
A hint, familiarize yourself again with the MIPS green card from the textbook.
Please pause the video and take a look at it again because we'll be using it in the
next slides.
Hopefully analyzing MIPS assembly code is fun because we'll be doing a little bit of
it this semester.
Please pause the video and work out what you think this code is doing.
It's computing the two's complement of a number stored in memory at the address contained
in register S0.
It's doing exactly what we would do if we were manually calculating it.
Invert all the bits by norring with zero and add one to it.
This is a good time to point out that MIPS doesn't have an invert instruction because
norring a value with the zero register accomplishes the same task.
Now let's play some code golf and reduce the number of instructions to get a fully optimized
program.
Code golf is slang for finding a minimal program to accomplish a task.
It's named after the sport of golf where the lowest score is the best score.
How else can MIPS compute two's complement?
Subtract our positive number from zero.
Load, transform, store.
It can't get any more succinct.
Let's jump into a little more complicated one.
Again, please pause the video and work it out.
This one required some work.
After loading the value from memory to T0, the SLT is one if it's less than zero, which
means the inverse is greater than or equal to zero.
Next we set T3 if our value is less than 4096.
The logical AND instruction will check that our value is both greater than or equal to
zero and less than 4096.
If it's true, it will not be zero, which means the branch instruction will take us to target.
Let's code golf this again.
This optimization is a bit sneaky.
Instead of performing multiple compares, it leverages the fact that 4096 is a power of
two so that the two's complement will contain ones in the most significant bits and zeros
in the bottom 12 least significant bits.
If our value in T1 is less than 4096, then any bits that are set will be set in bits
zero through 11.
So if we logically AND our value with T0, we'll get zero if there are no overlapping bits.
Success.
Can we do more?
Apparently yes.
MIPS gives us an SLT variant that takes a 16-bit intermediate value.
So if we treat our value as unsigned, meaning a negative number will be very large as the
signed bits are in the most significant bits, then we only need to do a single SLT before
branching.
Code golfing is useful in that it forces you to look at the full range of the ISA.
These minimal programs may come back in future exercises or exams, so please be sure to recognize
some of the double meanings presented here.
After all, knowing what SLTIU is doing under the hood will give you the insight required
to be a proficient ISA architect.